<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached for the funeral of that humble and faithful servant of Jesus Christ, Mr. Nathanael Smith late of Malmesbury, in the county of Wilts. : with a brief account of his life, in an epistle to Dr. Annesley / by Henry Chandler ...</title>
            <author>Chandler, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31657</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26770618</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26770618</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31657)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1712:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached for the funeral of that humble and faithful servant of Jesus Christ, Mr. Nathanael Smith late of Malmesbury, in the county of Wilts. : with a brief account of his life, in an epistle to Dr. Annesley / by Henry Chandler ...</title>
                  <author>Chandler, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Cockerill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCI [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Smith, Nathanael, d. 1691?</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  England.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached for the FUNERAL Of that Humble Faithful Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, Mr. <hi>NATHANAEL SMITH,</hi> LATE OF Malmesbury IN THE COUNTY of WILTS.</p>
            <p>WITH A Brief Account of his LIFE, in an Epiſtle to Dr. <hi>ANNESLY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY CHANDLER,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 112.6.</hi>
               </bibl> Surely he ſhall not be moved for ever: the righteous ſhall be in everlaſting remembrance.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Cockerill</hi> at the <hi>Three Leggs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Stocks Market.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109782:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109782:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend and Pious Dr. <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL ANNESLY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE deſign of this Application to you, is not your Praiſe; it were the greateſt Abſurdity for me to attempt it; for all that know you and me, know you to be much above my Character; your Works praiſe you better than my Pen can. My Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a ſincere and grateful Acknowledgment of the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I have received at your Hands, for which I ſtand much indebted to you. I would gladly bring a greater and better Thank-offering, were it in my Power; but this being the beſt, I hope it will be accepted; 'tis a Sermon preached for the Funeral of my Father-in-Law, whoſe virtuous good Life has done more to prefume his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, than this Printed Diſcourſe can do to perpetuate it. He was a Man eminently Religious, and very uſeful, a ſincere vigorous purſuer of Holineſs in his whole Courſe. I do ſeriouſly think, that if ever any man in the World made Religion his Buſineſs, he did; he was (ſo far as I could make Obſervation) Religious in every thing, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances for inſuperable Frailties being made. In his Cloſet he was frequent, and very ſerious, humble, and importunate in Prayer; if ever any Man prayed in ſeaſon and out of
<pb facs="tcp:109782:3"/>ſeaſon, he did; early and late did he wreſtle with God for himſelf, his Family, the Nation, and the Church of God: how early in the Morning have I heard him pleading with God for this poor Sinful Nation, when queſtionleſs he thought none in the Houſe was awake! Many an hours Sleep hath he denied himſelf of, for the ſake of private Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; many a cold Morning before Day hath he been upon his Knees without Fire or Candle, to do what in him lay to ſtave off Judgments from the poor Kingdom; how would he ſtir up himſelf, rouſe up his heart, and expoſtulate with his God! When I firſt ſaw him in his Coffin, I could not forbear ſaying, <hi>The Chariots of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof!</hi> In his private Retirements he was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully free and bold, yet not rude or irreverent in his Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>In his Family he was a conſtant zealous Worſhipper of God, Morning and Evening; no Buſineſs whatever could prevail with him either to omit or curtail his ſet ſolemn Family-Duties; a thing which I fear but few Profeſſors may pretend to. God's Word was read, his Name call'd on, his Praiſes ſung, as often in his Family, as perhaps in the beſt Families in <hi>England;</hi> I think but few Families ſo often mourned apart and together as his. I have reaſon to hope, that all his Children now living will bleſs God in Heaven for him. He was not (as too many Profeſſors are) chiefly careful to raiſe his Childrens Fortunes, but to ſave their Souls, and therefore was truly Watchful over them, and Faithful to them, as in the matter of Inſtruction, ſo alſo of Reproof and Correction. And here I may ſafely add, That he was one of the faithfulleſt Reprovers of Sin, that ever I knew. If in ſome Caſes his Zeal outran his Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wiſe Men will eaſily pardon it, as being a miſtake on the right hand. He was heartily concerned for the Glory of
<pb facs="tcp:109782:3"/>God, and could not endure to ſee or hear him diſhonoured; and therefore, tho he expoſed himſelf to danger, he would ſpeak without regarding the Perſon, or fearing the Iſſue.</p>
            <p>In the Congregation, he was a Devout, Serious Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; he loved God's Word, and honoured the Miniſtry; I have good reaſon to believe, that he uſually heard the Word Preached, in a very deep Humility and Self-denial: He took great pains to prepare his heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Word; and when he had heard it, he was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to keep it; and to that end, he would often repeat it in his Family, to his Wife and Children. I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it was his earneſt Deſire, to be in all things ſubject to the Law of God; for he was never offended at Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing, but loved to have his heart ripp'd up, and his ſins pointed at: He rejoiced in opportunities of drawing nigh to God; the Sabbaths were his Delight; and I judge he was one of the moſt ſtrict Obſervers of them. He had a great Veneration for the Miniſtry; I am well ſatisfied he hath done as much to maintain the Faithful Preaching of the Word in the Place he lived in, for many Years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as moſt of his Ability in <hi>England:</hi> I could give a particuldr account here, but that the Modeſty of his good Widow, my dear Mother-in-Law, forbids it. He was a Diſſenter from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and uſually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the Miniſtry of <hi>Nonconformiſts;</hi> but an hearty Lover, and ready Hearer of all Sober, Orthodox, well-living <hi>Conformiſts;</hi> a thing, I judge, very commendable, as ſavouring of a Catholick Spirit, and proceeding from true Chriſtian Charity.</p>
            <p>In his Buſineſs he was Diligent, but not Sollicitous. I never ſaw a man commit his ways to God, with a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Confidence and Truſt. He was induſtriouſly careful to be religiouſly careleſs. He took indeed true pains to
<pb facs="tcp:109782:4"/>get this World; but I think in my conſcience, very much without vexatious thoughtfulneſs in the purſuit; raiſing delight in the getting, or ſinking grief for the loſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. In his dealings he was punctual and juſt; true to his word, and conſcionable in his ways; he was careful rather to receive than do wrong, as many in the City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey can ſafely teſtifie. He lived not in Pleaſure, but was ridgidly Temperate; and for the ſake of Religious Duties, did very much deny himſelf in Eating and Drinking.</p>
            <p>He was truly Charitable, and ready to relieve the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed; he thought it his Duty, and made it his Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to lay up for Charitable and Pious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes, as God had bleſſed him; and what he laid up, he counted no more his own, than a bag of his Neighbour's Money that might be left with him; ſo grateful was doing good to him, that he not only did it chearfully himſelf, but rejoiced exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, to obſerve others like-minded. He was mightily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with thoſe that harboured the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants; and ſent a Thouſand Prayers to Heaven for them: The Concerns of the Church lay near his heart; and had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly a room in his Prayers.</p>
            <p>He was conſtantly Serious; he ſeemed to carry a dread of the Majeſty of God continually upon his Spirit; and would be frequently putting in ſomething of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he was, or whomſoever he was converſing with; and that which crown'd all, is, he was profoundly humble, as ſenſible of his own <hi>Nothingneſs,</hi> as moſt men that ever I knew. In a word, as was his Name, ſo was he, an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, <hi>in whom there was no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reverend Sir,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot but preſume, That you will readily grant, upon a Suppoſition that this Account is true, (as God knoweth
<pb facs="tcp:109782:4"/>it is), That he was a very good man; and conſent, That his Name ſhould be kept alive, and his good Example recorded for others Imitation. For this End, I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured thus to appear in Publick, by Printing this well-meaning poor Diſcourſe; which I humbly lay at your Feet, as a Token of my unfeigned Gratitude for your undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Love to me. The Lord recompence you; Bleſs this Eſſay to the Souls of them that ſhall read it; and incline your Heart to Pray for</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>May <hi>8. 1691.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Obliged, Humble Servant, <hi>HENRY CHANDLER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:109782:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109782:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB I. 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>—The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words acquaint us with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable good Temper of Soul that Religious <hi>Job</hi> poſſeſſed in the midſt of an unparallell'd Affliction. His caſe was thus: A moſt tremendous Hurricane of Providence had overturned and ſwept away almoſt all his earthly Comforts; his Oxen and Aſſes were ſeiz'd by the <hi>Saheans,</hi> his Sheep deſtroyed by Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, his Camels carried away by the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> his Servants ſlain; and which was worſt of all, his dearer Children unhappily taken away in the midſt of their Mirth; and the terrible Advice hereof brought him in Parcels by Meſſengers one upon the heels of another in one day. A thing ſo dreadful, that at firſt ſight one would think it was a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of Providence to make as great and diſmal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction amongſt his Graces within, as it did amongſt his Goods and Chattels, and Children without; and indeed this was the deſign of Satan, but not of God, as will appear to the ſerious Conſiderer of the meek
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109782:6"/>and compoſed Remark he makes upon the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Words of my Text, <hi>The Lord,</hi> &amp;c. where he doth not only implicitly acquit God of all Unrighteouſneſs or Cruelty, but expreſsly praiſe and bleſs him. A frame of heart as ſignally and wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy, as God's Providence was dreadful and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conſider this Practice of <hi>Job,</hi> not only as a matter of Hiſtory, but as an example of Piety, propoſed to us by the Holy Ghoſt for our imitation. And then they afford us this Obſervation.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>Every Chriſtian is indiſpenſibly obliged to bleſs the afflicting taking God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall endeavour to give you the Senſe, manifeſt the Truth, and ſhew you the Uſefulneſs of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>In the Explication of the Doctrine, I ſhall firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſome miſtakes, and ſhew what is not the Senſe of it: As,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) This Doctrine doth not mean, that we ſhould love our Afflictions for their own ſake;<note place="margin">Malum qua malum non eſt appeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile.</note> I humbly conceive, that this is impracticable, and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion obliges us not to the Practice of things ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely impoſible, as is the loving any Evil as Evil; Pain, Loſs, Poverty, Sickneſs or Death, <hi>cannot</hi> be loved for themſelves; 'tis repugnant even to innocent Nature; Chriſt Jeſus himſelf could not practice it, as we are taught by that Expreſſion,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.39.</note> 
               <hi>If it be poſſible, let this cup paſs from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109782:6"/>
            <p>Neither, (2.) Doth this Doctrine deſignedly plead for a Stoical impenetrableneſs, as tho it were a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to be inſenſible of, and unconcerned at the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of Providence; this is very alien from the Senſe of the Holy Ghoſt, the Frame of <hi>Job,</hi> or the Deſign of this Sermon: As the firſt is impracticable; this is inhumane, if not impracticable too; for by the way, I think as few of the <hi>Stoicks</hi> arrived to their admired <hi>Apathy,</hi> as Quakers to their pretended Perfection.</p>
            <p>However, to entertain the Rebukes of Providence with a moderate proportioned ſorrowful Reſentment, I account virtuous and commendable. <hi>Job</hi> himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth ſomewhat of this nature, by rending his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, ſhaving his Head, and falling down upon the ground. And God teacheth us this Leſſon, by creating us with a Diſpoſition to grieve when his Providences call for it, for God maketh nothing in vain; then what need of Water and Sluices, if the one muſt never run, nor the other ever be drawn?</p>
            <p>But affirmatively, the Doctrine doth intend,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) When God afflicts us by taking away from us, we muſt carefully prevent or ſuppreſs all quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Diſcontent; we are bound to ſee that there be no Rebels in our Hearts that find fault with God, or that riſe up and charge him fooliſhly; 'tis our Duty to keep the King of Heaven's Peace in our Souls at ſuch times; to watch carefully againgſt Tumults and Mutinies in our Hearts, which are ever and anon apt to riſe at the leaſt Provocation imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yea many times, when there is none given at all. Here I conceive are two things to be minded.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109782:7"/>(1.) In all our Afflictions we muſt take heed, that we do not raſhly and proudly call our God to account concerning his Providences; for he is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely above us, and <hi>who dare ſay unto him, What doeſt thou?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 9.12.</note> If we cannot underſtand the Wiſdom or Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of his Methods;<note place="margin">Watſon.</note> we muſt ſilently <hi>adore, where we cannot fathom,</hi> and patiently wait till he unvail them. The Examination of a God is not the Province of a Creature; though we may humbly enquire for our own Inſtruction, yet we may not proudly ask for Examination. This is more than his Angels ever durſt pretend to.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) We muſt be as careful, that in our Judgment made upon his Providence, we reflect not upon his Attributes. In the Language of Scripture, that we do not attribute Folly to God; we may not in <hi>any caſe</hi> think that God hath forgot himſelf, or acts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like himſelf; for if we ſhould, 'twould be nothing leſs than ſpeaking Blaſphemy in our Hearts, whoſe Words are as audible to God as thoſe of our Mouths. If I miſtake not, the Religious <hi>Aaron</hi> lived both theſe Particulars, when being afflicted ſeverely by the Lord in the Death of his two Sons,<note place="margin">Lev. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>He held his peace;</hi> his profound ſilence loudly ſpeaking a Reſolution in him, not to examine nor impeach the Great and Holy God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Our bleſſing the afflicting taking God, includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a readineſs in us to proclaim the Righteouſneſs and Juſtice of all his afflictive Diſpenſations. In all our Diſtreſſes and Sorrows, 'tis our Duty to think and acknowledge that God hath not wronged us, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the demerits of our Sins; but that we truly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109782:7"/>deſerve the ſtrokes we ſmart under, be they never ſo many; thus the poor afflicted Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> acknowledgeth, and ſo will every gracious Soul; and thus doth <hi>Job</hi> himſelf, <hi>If I juſtify my ſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 9.13. Job 9.20.</note> 
               <hi>mine own mouth ſhall condemn me: If I ſay, I am perfect, it ſhall alſo prove me perverſe.</hi> A gracious heart will juſtify God, tho by ſo doing he unavoidably throws dirt in his own face; he deſires to honour God by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, tho it be to his own diſparagement; as he rejoyces to ſee the Sun riſe, tho it put out the Moon, and all the Stars.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Our bleſſing the afflicting taking God, includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our abſolute Subjection to his Sovereign will. Here be two things.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) 'Tis our duty to believe that God <hi>ought</hi> to have an unlimited Dominion over us and ours; to uſe and diſpoſe as ſeemeth good to him; this is an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of God's right. Thus <hi>Job</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>Behold he taketh away, who can hinder him? who will ſay unto him, what doeſt thou?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 9.12.</note> Which words deſcribe to us not only God's irreſiſtible Power, but his unqueſtionable Authority; <hi>none can, none ought</hi> to oppoſe him; now in our Afflictions eſpecially, we ſhould firmly believe this, That God <hi>may</hi> take away our Yoke-fellows, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Health, Eſtates, or what he pleaſe, from us; 'tis his <hi>Right</hi> to diſpoſe of us and ours.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) 'Tis our duty freely and fully to conſent, that God <hi>ſhall</hi> exerciſe this Dominion over us and ours. The firſt Particular I told you, was an acknowledging of God's right. This ſecond, is a rendring him his due. The one we learn by the Light of Nature; the other is only performed by the help of Special Grace.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109782:8"/>We ſhould unreſervedly devote all our Comforts to his Sovereign diſpoſal, lay all our Enjoyments, by ſincere reſignation, at his feet, as the Diſciples did the Price of their Eſtates at the Feet of the Apoſtles.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.35.</note> When God cometh for any one of thy Comforts, 'tis thy Duty, Chriſtian, like <hi>Araunah</hi> the <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> to give like a King,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.23.</note> unto thy King the Lord of Hoſts; thou ſhouldeſt ſay to God, as he to <hi>David, Let my Lord take,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>and offer up to his own will, what ſeemeth good unto him.</hi> Thus the good old <hi>Eli</hi> replieth to <hi>Samuel, It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> In which Words, he doth not only ſubmit to the ſlaughter of his Sons, and the rejection of his Family from the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood for ever (a terrible Providence) but alſo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, that if he had yet another Comfort left, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of which would glorifie God, that alſo was heartily at his ſervice. Lord, how little of this is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the generality of profeſſing Chriſtians! Yet this is our Duty; and queſtionleſs this was holy <hi>Job</hi>'s practice, and it ſhould be ours daily. When God is taking away any of our Comforts, we ſhould be ſo far from wreſting them out of God's hands, that we ſhould moſt unfeignedly offer them all.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our bleſſing the afflicting taking God, includeth our heedful converſing with the Divine Goodneſs and Mercy, that ever manageth all our Afflictions; I intreat you, let this be carefully conſidered. <hi>All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25.10.</note> 
               <hi>unto ſuch as keep his covenant, and his teſtimonies.</hi> Even the frowns of his Providence as well as the ſmiles, theſe are not only juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but merciful and faithful; yea (the Lord help our unbelief) mercy and truth in the abſtract. Now
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109782:8"/>God expects that we firmly believe it, carefully obſerve it, and gratefully acknowledge it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we firmly believe it: God never deceiveth us, therefore we ſhould never miſtruſt him; God cannot be deceived, he is too wife for that; he cannot deceive, he is too juſt for that: Therefore when God tells us, that however he deals with us, he is ever mindful of, and true to his Word in every Providence, we muſt honour him by believing; we ſhould ſay, O my ſoul, though thy God taketh away this, and that, and the other comfort, yet 'tis in love, mercy and truth, for he hath promiſed, he will never car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it otherwiſe towards thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we carefully obſerve it; That we endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to <hi>taſte</hi> and <hi>ſee</hi> that the Lord is good in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting us. God <hi>hath ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8.</note> he will be good to us in every Providence, therefore we ſhould believe it; God <hi>is</hi> good to us in every Providence, therefore we ſhould obſerve and ſee it. 'Tis as really a fault to ſhut our eyes, as our ears. When God afflicts us, we obſerve his anger, tell his ſtrokes, and pore upon his ſeverity, but neglect to heed his mercy in the Providence; but this is our fault; we ſhould as impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially ſtudy the uſefulneſs, as the pain of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction: A wiſe Patient will as much conſider the wholſome tendency of his Phyſick, as its griping o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) That we gratefully acknowledge it. 'Tis our duty to thank and praiſe the Lord for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us, in afflicting of us: This indeed is diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but 'tis as glorious when done; 'tis a Duty,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.18.</note> and muſt be done. In <hi>every</hi> thing we muſt give thanks,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109782:9"/>for this is the will of God in Chriſt Jeſus, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us. What, may ſome ſay, muſt we give thanks for our ſorrows,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.20.</note> griefs and preſſures? muſt we thank God for ſtripping, ſcourging and wounding us? I anſwer, ſo ſaith the Scripture, giving thanks always for <hi>all things</hi> unto God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You'll be ready to ſay, this is an hard Leſſon, who can learn it? You, by the grace of God, quickly, if you conſider and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the reaſon offer'd, in above mentioned 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. <hi>This is the will of God in Chriſt Jeſus, concerning you:</hi> where I conceive the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> would have us know, that every Providence, the adverſe, as well as proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, is the gracious management of a God in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, proceeding not from meer juſtice, but love and faithfulneſs; and that therefore the Saints are as much obliged to praiſe God for the one, as for the other; becauſe their true intereſt is equally promoted by both; as a man is as truly beholden to his Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that cuts off his gangreen'd Leg, as to him that lends a Fillet to help bind it up. I cannot therefore but admire the profoundneſs of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Judgment, who thinks that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> did not fully reach the Sence of the Holy Ghoſt in this Text; who, to theſe Words, <hi>This is the will of God;</hi> adds only, <hi>Nempe ut gratias agamus:</hi> and therefore gives a more full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them in the following Words. <hi>Ego plenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſenſum contineri puto his verbis, quod talis ſit erga nos, Dei affectus in Chriſto ut in afflictionibus quoque largam habeamus materiam gratias agendi;</hi> God is moſt certainly kind and good to his people when he afflicts them; ſure then in point of gratitude, they can do no leſs than acknowledge it to him and others.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109782:9"/>(1.) To him. Every kindneſs deſerves thanks: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are God's Kindneſſes to the Saints, and therefore they ſhould thank him for them. We thank God for our Food; what hinders, but that we ſhould thank him for our Phyſick too? A good Man once put up a Bill to me to this effect, <hi>Sir, my Family is ſorely viſited with Sickneſs, I deſire you would bleſs God on my behalf.</hi> I read the Note, and being amazed at the unuſualneſs an ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of it, did not acquaint the People with the Contents of it; but (knowing who wrote it) after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards asked the Perſon what he meant? Whether he had not miſtaken? He told me, No, he thought himſelf obliged to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood God, that he would take ſo much notice of him, as to afflict him for his good. When I heard that, I as much wondered at his extraordinary Piety, as at his unuſual Bill. This is little practiſed, but is certainly the Duty of all the Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) To others. The Holy <hi>David</hi> records the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of an afflicting God, and proclaims his Praiſe to all the World,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71, 75.</note> 
               <hi>In very faithfulneſs haſt thou afflicted me. 'Twas well for me, that I was afflicted, that I might learn thy precepts.</hi> And without diſpute, 'tis what honours God, and would edify his People. Thus I have given you the Senſe of the Doctrine, the ſum of which take in theſe few Words:</p>
            <p>'Tis the indiſpenſible Duty of every Chriſtian, when afflicted of God, compoſedly to bear his Hand, readily to ſubmit to his Will, careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vindicate his Juſtice, firmly to believe, heedfully to obſerve, and thankfully to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109782:10"/>his mercy and faithfulneſs in the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>The next thing in order, is to ſhew the Truth of this Doctrine, which were altogether needleſs, but that we are naturally purblind, and cannot ſee the things of our Duty, unleſs by many Arguments, Reaſons, and Similitudes, they be brought very near to us. Otherwiſe, what needs any Arguments to prove that we muſt not repine at, or reflect upon God? That we muſt not rebel againſt, or be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful to him? The thing may be clearly ſeen at a great diſtance by its own light; but we have bad Eyes, and they muſt be helped. I ſhall therefore offer ſome things to put us paſt doubt, <hi>That we ought, &amp;c.</hi>—</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) However we are afflicted, 'tis certain, we ſhould not murmur, becauſe we are not injured. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member here what hath been plainly hinted already; 'tis not forbidden that we cry out. God that made us Men, ne're obliged us to be Blocks; that that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, is this, that in our complaints we find no fault with <hi>Him,</hi> make no diſhonourable Reflections upon <hi>Him.</hi> The word rendred <hi>complain,</hi> in <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.39. doth moſt uſually ſignify <hi>murmuring;</hi> is ſo rendred in the Margin of ſome Bibles, and I judg in that Sence to be underſtood in that Text. Surely we may cry under God's Rod, but we muſt not cry againſt his Hand; for all that he brings upon us, is juſtly brought upon us; and why ſhould we reproach him that worketh Righteouſneſs? Sith God dealeth fairly (and he cannot do otherwiſe) we have no reaſon to talk
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109782:10"/>foul againſt him. 'Tis time enough to find fault when we are wrong'd; till then all murmuring is unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, whatever we ſuffer. Hence by the way we may obſerve, That as there is no juſt ground for it on Earth, ſo neither is there in Hell; for there God <hi>wrongs</hi> not the damned Wretches, how ſeverely ſoever he handles them.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) 'Tis as plain, that in all our Afflictions we ought readily to proclaim the Righteouſneſs of God, holding our peace; and refraining from diſcontent and murmuring is not enough, we ought to open our mouths and praiſe God, even for his righteouſneſs and truth in afflicting us; becauſe there can never be any reaſon given why God ſhould loſe his Glory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have ſinned away our Comfort. Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is a Duty, as we are reaſonable Creatures, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of obſerving and proclaiming the glorious Perfections of his Nature and Works; and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as we are humoured, pleaſed, and accommodated with the good things of this Life; or elſe the rich, healthy, and proſperous only, were obliged to do him Honour, which we are ſo far from granting, that no Man in his Wits will ever deſire that we ſhould.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Nor is it leſs clear, That in all ſuch Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences we ought readily to ſubmit to his will, becauſe otherwiſe we are</p>
            <q>
               <l>Rebels againſt our King.</l>
               <l>Falſe to our Covenant.</l>
               <l>Enemies to our true Intereſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:109782:11"/>(1.) We are <hi>Rebels againſt our King.</hi> I would hope it were needleſs here to inſiſt upon the Right God hath to manage us, and all our concerns: He is our Lord and Sovereign upon the moſt indiſputable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts that can be; he is our Creator, we have our Being from him; our Benefactor, we have our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from him; he made us, he maintains us, and now can there poſſibly be any reaſon given, why he ſhould not govern us, or diſpoſe of us? I think 'tis paſt all doubt, that God is our rightful abſolute Lord, and if ſo, then ſurely we ought to obey, and comply with his Will in all things; and when we do not, we Rebel againſt him.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) We are <hi>falſe to our Covenant.</hi> We have <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed</hi> to ſubmit to his Will; we have more than once or twice avouched the Lord for our Maſter and King, and given up our ſelves to him, to be ruled, and managed by him as he ſhall ſee good; we have renounced our own Wills, and taken his Will for our Law, and therefore <hi>in point of Fidelity</hi> we are bound readily to comply with the Will of an afflicting God; if we do not, we are guilty of moſt vile falſeneſs and perfidy.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) We are <hi>Enemies to our true Intereſt.</hi> Which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently lies in our being managed by an infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Truth, and Goodneſs, and ſuch is God. He that had rather govern himſelf, than be governed by his God, is (without Exception) a Fool, and an Enemy to himſelf. However God deals with his People, 'tis clear as the Sun, they cannot be better managed; for if any can manage them better, it muſt be by reaſon of more wiſdom, and more goodneſs; and good Lord! where ſhould they have it? Can the Rivers have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109782:11"/>more water than the Sea? Or have they any but what they have from the Sea?</p>
            <p>As to the Fourth Particular, I judge, that the Text in the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and the other in the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> do ſufficiently prove it: I ſhall therefore paſs to the Uſes, which ſhall be Five Inferences, and One Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Application.</hi> Is it the Duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then (1.) This helps to diſcover, that the generality of Profeſſors of the Chriſtian Religion, are very great ſcandals to the Religion they Profeſs; or that Chriſtianity is very little lived by the generality of its Profeſſors, who can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrive to a ſerious thankfulneſs in the midſt of their Peace and Plenty; and when at any time they are tryed by Afflictive Providences, are ſo far from an Heavenly well pleaſedneſs with the Wiſe and Good will of God, that their fooliſh Souls diſcover not only diſcontent, but Diſloyalty and Rebellion againſt the Sovereign of their Lives and Mercies: What the Devil falſly inſinuated againſt <hi>Job</hi> 1 <hi>ch.</hi> 9, 10. he may truly ſay of moſt Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſerve God for his good things; their love to God is a mercenary baſe love; when God is Loved and Praiſed only or chiefly for the ſake of his Creatures wherewith he benefits them; and this is apparent, in that many Perſons can hardly find matter of Praiſe to God any longer than his Sun ſhines, and his Showers fall on them. When God hath done for a ſeaſon pouring down his favours upon them in that large meaſure as heretofore, they have done alſo Praiſing of Him, till the next convenient oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. If God turn his hand, they can turn their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109782:12"/>tongues from Thankſgiving, to Quarrelling; from Praiſe, to Diſcontent, if not Blaſphemy and Curſing. You may aſſure your ſelves, this is quite another thing than true Religion. For</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) This Doctrine plainly ſheweth us, That 'tis our Duty to Love God for himſelf, and all Creatures in Subordination to him: For here you ſee the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Edomite <hi>Job</hi> Loving and Praiſing his God, when he had hardly a Creature-comfort left him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe pleaſantly with; and what ſhould hinder? He good man loved the Creature, but as a ſtep by which he may aſcend to the Creator, and if that were took away, he needed it not, if the Lord would ſtoop to his Soul, or lift up his Soul to himſelf. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if we ſee any more than a <hi>ſubordinate rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fulneſs</hi> in the Creature, 'tis becauſe the Devil hath ſet up a falſe light in our Souls; and if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the creature principally for any other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than becauſe they help us to Know and Love God, we proſtitute our Souls to an Idol. If it be our Duty to Love and Praiſe God when he ſtrips us of Creature-Comforts, then ſurely we are to Love Him for Himſelf, and His Creatures in a direct ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to Him; when we have them, we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce more that God is Glorified by His Bounty to us, than that we are accommodated; and when he takes them away, we ſhould rejoyce that he is Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by His Sovereingty over us, though we be not accommodated.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) This teacheth us, That there is no <hi>ſuch worth</hi> in Creature-enjoyments as we uſually imagine: That all things that God hath made, are very good, having the footſteps of Divine Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109782:12"/>imprinted on them, is paſt all queſtion, and I readily grant; and that there is a ſuitable agreeing conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the good things of this life to mans neceſſities in this Animal ſtate, I cannot deny; but that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in themſelves, and with reſpect to Man, are leſs good than prejudiced Sinners do uſually conceive, is certain from Scripture and daily experience, in as much as the one frequently tells us, they are all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the other as frequently finds it ſo. Yet men purſue them (I mean Meat, Drink, Eſtates, Yokefel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as furiouſly as if they were undone if they had them not; and enjoy them ſo extravagantly and abuſively as if they had no other good to ſpend their Souls upon; which if it were true, God would never make it our Duty to part with them with rejoycing, as he doth in this Text, and in the 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.16, 18. That there is leſs good in the Creature therefore than we uſually think, is evident from this, that it may be our intereſt to be without them, and our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Bleſs God when he takes them away; O that this may abide for ever upon your hearts!</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) This ſhews, That 'tis the trueſt Wiſdom to get an heart mortified to the World, I mean to have one's Soul poſſeſs an even Spiritual temper in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of Providence, ſo as not to be charmed or inveigled with the delights of Proſperity, or be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed or grieved at the little annoyances of adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Muſt we Bleſs and Praiſe and Love God, when he takes away our comforts? then ſurely 'tis our Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom not to be exceſſively pleaſed when he gives them. 'Tis certainly a Vanity to Love the Preſence of that much, which with chearfulneſs we muſt bid farewell the next time the Giver calls for it; he lives moſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109782:13"/>that lives moſt ſoberly with reſpect to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Comforts; becauſe as he beſt reliſheth the Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them, and moſt perfectly knows the true taſt of them, ſo he is beſt fitted to manage his Duty at their departure. If a man with <hi>Micah,</hi> 18 <hi>Judges</hi> 24. Converts his Gold and Silver into a God, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if he run crying like a mad man after the Idol, when the true God takes it away. Whereas the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Heavenly Soul can eaſily part with it, becauſe he knew it, and comparatively deſpiſed it before.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) This ſhews us, that 'tis an Evil to <hi>indulge</hi> a Grief at the loſs of Earthly comforts. I have told you already, that the Text doth not preſcribe a ſtupid Stoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm. But to admit a Grief too near, or entertain it too long for any Creature, is unbecoming a Servant of Chriſt, and a Profeſſor of Religion; <hi>to ſorrow as thoſe without hope,</hi> as in 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13. is expreſſed, is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a very great Sin, let the loſs be what it will; when perſons ſorrow is ſo great, that it breaks their Spirits, unfits them for Communion with God, and deſtroys their Health; when they Grieve as if they were undone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this is certainly very evil; or elſe when perſons have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver done Grieving, but like fooliſh <hi>Jonah</hi> think they do well to be angry with God, yea to be angry to the death, as in <hi>Jon.</hi> 3.9. this is Horrid and Abominable. How far are ſuch perſons from the right frame! Sinners take but little notice of this thing; but certainly where this frame doth prevail, it beſpeaks a great deal of untamed pride in a Perſon; and ſignifies that there is very little Grace, if any at all in ſuch a Soul. A Godly, Soul may be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, and or ever he is aware, carried far into an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant paſſion of Grief, but uſually is ſomewhat com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed after the firſt ſtorm; but a long tedious fixed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109782:13"/>Grief for the loſs of any Creature, ſhews either that the Soul never knew any thing greater than his Creature-comforts; or elſe that he is very much ſunk into a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual diſtemper, and for the preſent hath forgot the reliſh of Divine Conſolation.</p>
            <p>I now paſs to the laſt Uſe, and it is this.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Carefully endeavour to diſpoſe your ſelves to entertain Afflictive Providences, as you ought, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving congruouſly of them aforehand. My Brethren, You are in a good meaſure ready for the bittereſt Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and fitted to receive the ſaddeſt Revolution whatever, if you habitually conceive aright of an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſtate: I mean, if you uſually hit the nature and end of ſuch Providences in your apprehenſions about them. The Evils of this life, as they are managed for the Godly, are not by far ſo dreadful when fully underſtood, as at firſt ſight they did appear; certainly the reaſon why good Chriſtians tremble at the approach of Temporal Evils, is becauſe they do not know them; as heretofore the Poor Diſciples cryed out, when Chriſt came on the Sea to them, as if a deſtroying Devil had been coming aboard the Ship; whereas when they knew who 'twas, one of them dares go upon the waters that he may meet him. Many times a Godly Soul looketh upon an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Calamity with Conſternation and Terrour, that he entertains with Profit, and reviews with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Pleaſure; and ſaith with <hi>David Pſal.</hi> 119.71. <hi>'Twas good for me, that I was afflicted, &amp;c.</hi> As a Pleure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Perſon is ready to dye when he ſees the Surgeon and Lancet, who notwithſtanding finds eaſe whilſt the Blood runs, and afterwards rejoyceth that 'tis done. Therefore let me entreat you that fear the Lord, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109782:14"/>to conceive aright of all the ſeverities of your Heavenly Father; and here I ſhall offer you theſe helps.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) You may be confident, that however he afflicts you, he deſigns not to ſatisfie His Juſtice by any thing He inflicts upon you: and therefore he will not wound you either in Extremity, or to Eternity. When God Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the Reprobate part of the World, He is demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfaction of them; and hence it is, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly tell how much, or how long it is they ſhall ſuffer.</p>
            <p>But 'tis not ſo with the Saints, their Surety hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered the demands of juſtice in their ſtead; and God will not, yea in juſtice cannot require it of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, when he hath already received it of the Surety; and that Jeſus Chriſt did ſatisfie the Father for the Sins of the Elect, is one of the Articles of our Creed; and we are not Chriſtians if we queſtion it. God acknowldgeth it in <hi>Job</hi> 33.24. as alſo in that he raiſed him up from the dead, and admitted him into Heaven: every Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver therefore may aſſure himſelf, that however God deal with him, He deſigns not to ſatisfie His juſtice upon him, nor intends to give the demerit of his Sins to him.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Whatever ſad Providence befal you, God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no proper loſs, or real damage ſhall befall you; no Revolutions ſhall Impoveriſh or Spoil a Servant of Jeſus; for though the Enemy in Perſecution, may take away his Worldly goods, he is no more damnified, than he is whoſe houſe is emptied of worthleſs lumber, that he may come at his Cupboard or Coffers. Though a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109782:14"/>Diſtemper take away his eaſe or ſtrength, he is not hurt, for the Grace he receives inſtead thereof, doth more than make him amends.</p>
            <p>Affliction takes nothing away from a Gracious Soul, but what is better miſſed than had; and therefore though it takes all his days he is never the poorer. A Gracious Perſon hath but Three things worth the keeping, and thoſe no Enemy ſhall take away. (1.) His Soul. (2.) His Grace. (3.) His God.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) His Soul; which though it may by Death be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Body; yet ſhall it never be in the hands of an Enemy: I mean, under the Tyranny of the World, Fleſh, or Devil, <hi>for the Lord will redeem the Souls of his ſervants, Pſal.</hi> 34.22. Tho the Cabinet may by an undiſtinguiſhing Providence be thrown here and there, yet God will take care of the Precious Jewel, That that be not loſt.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) His Grace; which indeed is the only bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Jewel; this the Soul ſhall never be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally deprived of. <hi>John</hi> 4.14. This ſpark is kindled by Heaven, and all the breath of Hell, and Water on Earth ſhall never quench it. God hath ſet this plant, and it will grow in all Weathers, for Almighty Power protects it; whatever a Believer loſes, he never lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Image of God; that cannot be loſt.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) His God; Who though he may hide His Face, yet will not deny his Covenant, nor forget that he is the Believer's God by a ſure deed of Gift; all the World can no more deprive a Believer of His God, than they can deprive God of Himſelf, <hi>for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death uor life,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 8.38. now this being believed and conſidered, there is not ſo much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109782:15"/>of Terror in any Providence to a Soul that hath repented of Sin, and Believed in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) What Troubles ſoever come upon you, are in the account of infinite Wiſdom needful for you, to the carrying on your Sanctification, and fitting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>you for the life of Heaven; as you may ſee in the 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.6. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God appoints no Viſitation for his People, but what is neceſſary for them; not but that God could ſave them another way; for he can make his People perfectly Holy, and take them to Heaven the ſame inſtant he converts them; but he hath not ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, neither dare we ſay or think it would be beſt that he ſhould; that way and method that God hath ſet for the ſaving of his People, requires that in this ſtate they be exerciſed with various afflictions, to fit them for a better. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22. What though we cannot ſee the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency of ſuch Troubles? muſt they therefore be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs? God's ways are not as our ways, nor his thoughts, as our thoughts; if he ſaith they be needful for us, 'tis our Duty as Creatures and Chriſtians to do honour to his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom, by a chearful compliance with his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Should God ſtop the courſe of nature, and give us continually dry warm weather, becauſe we think there is no need of ſhowers or froſts, the World were undone; and as certainly ſhould we be in great want, did God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all thoſe evils He inflict without our Approbation. Chriſtian, firmly believe it, for it is certainly true, That thou never felteſt any pain, ſufferedſt any damage, met'ſt with any Trouble, underwenteſt any Perſecution, but what was truly proper for thee in thy Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, but what thou didſt really want as an hungry Man wants Bread, or a ſick Man Phyſick. And aſſure thy ſelf, thou nor the Church of Chriſt ſhall ever ſmart
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109782:15"/>under any new grief, till you ſtand in real need of it. <hi>For he doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men,</hi> Lam. 3.33. God delighth not to afflict any of the Children of Men without cauſe, much leſs will he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet his own dear Children, but when he ſees it will promote his Glory, and their Good. This one Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration would be of mighty force to quiet our Souls in the moſt diſmal day, if ſeriouſly weighed, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed by us.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) It may be the Evils you feel or fear. Chriſt Jeſus hath ſuffered before you. Are you poor? So was he without Eſtate or Money, as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27. Are you deſpiſed? So was he, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.3. Are you dejected in Spirit, tempted of Satan, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted of God, perſecuted of Men? Why all this did the bleſſed Redeemer ſuffer before you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.38. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Math.</hi> 27.46, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is it ſuch an heinous thing that God ſhould deal with us as he hath with his only begotten Eternal well-beloved Son? Did our Lord and Maſter conflict with Sufferings whilſt in this Life, and ſhall we be offended unleſs we go free? Why ſhould we think it much to pledge Jeſus Chriſt? What, tho it be a bitter Draught, 'tis not deſtructive Poyſon, otherwiſe the Son of God would never have put it to his Lips. We ſhould not have ſuch black thoughts of ſuffering, did we conſider that a God-man was was the greateſt ſufferer on Earth, yea, a greater than any in Hell.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) God hath not laid upon you any Burthen, but what he has tried other Saints with before; and ſo he ſerves you as he ſerves the reſt of his Children, and why ſhould you expect to fare better than your Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows? <hi>There hath no temptation happened to you, but ſuch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109782:16"/>as is common to men,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.13. And ſure this ſhould qualify you, that God hath not ſingled you out as eminent inſtances of extraordinary Indignation. Oh! that this may fit us for all God's will, and mould us into an holy Compliance with his Sovereign Pleaſure. If God bring the Sword upon us, and deſtroy us by War, he hath dealt ſo already with <hi>France, Hungary, Ireland,</hi> and other Chriſtian Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; and we are not better than they; 'twill be well for us, if we be not found worſe than any of them.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Whatever Calamity he viſits you with, he will mightily ſupport you under, and maintain you in. When God bringeth his People into the Wilderneſs, he doth not leave them there to make their Party good in their own ſtrength, (if he did, they were undone) but ſtands by and aſſiſts them according to his good word, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.2. And indeed ſuch ſweet Experience have the Saints had of God's faithfulneſs in this matter, that in the midſt of their Sufferings, they have forgot where they were, and have been even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of Torture, whilſt it hath been inflicting. Nay one, when he was let down from the Rack, was even ſorry that he was to be tortured no longer.— And the ſame promiſes that were made good to them, are given to you; therefore think not unbecomingly of any Affliction, <hi>For this God is your God for ever and ever: he will be your guide even unto death,</hi> as in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 48.14. Say not you are weak, and ſhall ſink under the weight of your Affliction, for his Power ſhall be made known, and in him you ſhall be able to do or ſuffer all things.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:109782:16"/>(7.) Whatever Affliction God doth viſit you with, he will exceedingly profit you by, for by it he will convey an encreaſe of Grace, and fitneſs for Glory; therefore let it not ſeem ſo terrible to you, to be in Poverty, Sickneſs, Pain, and Perſecution, if thereby you may be made more like God, and fitted for the heavenly Glory.</p>
            <p n="8">(8.) Whatever trouble God brings you into, he will bring you victorious out of; for with the Temptation he will provide a way for eſcape, <hi>that ye maybe able to hear it,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.13. Your Tryals, as they are not extream, ſo they ſhall not be everlaſting, (as before) but either he will deliver you alive or dead; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps God will yet ſpare you to enjoy a Tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a proſperous State with the Church here on Earth, and give you quiet from your Troubles all round about, according to that in <hi>Joſhua</hi> 22.44. or which is far better, take your Souls to the World of Reſt and Peace, where you ſhall be out of Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">(9.) All your Troubles ſhall turn to your account in the other World, being managed to the Glory of God by you in this, through the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of Grace. God will not forget that Humility, Brokenneſs, Self-reſignation, and Faith, that you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe under all your Afflictions, but will plentifully reward all another day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2, 3, 19. God takes notice how the gracious Soul acteth Grace in tryal, and is well-pleaſed with it, deſigns it a bleſſed recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, ſo that a ſtate of Affliction ſhould not be thought ſo terrible by you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:109782:17"/>
            <head>An Acroſtical EPITAPH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>ature defil'd with Sin, haraſs'd with Pain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> while diſſolved is; 'Twill meet again,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T</hi>hroughly refin'd, and perfectly at eaſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H</hi>eal'd of all Sin, and cur'd of all Diſeaſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Body ſpeaks.</note>
                  <hi>A</hi>bove the higheſt Star my Soul is gone,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>o where to ſtay, till to the holy One.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>ll Love and Praiſe ſhe offers on her Knee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>ncompaſſed with Heavens Nobility.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>ong 'twill not be ere Chriſt ſhall fetch me there,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>ound as his Angels, ſweet as Heavens Air.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M</hi>any a day we both pray'd for this thing;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> mean to ſee enthron'd Heaven's Glorious King.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'T</hi>is not in vain to pray, my Soul <hi>doth ſee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H</hi>er Lord, and I <hi>expect</hi> that Liberty.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
            <p>THe Reaſonableneſs of Perſonal Reformation, and the neceſſity of Converſion: the true Methods of making all Men happy in this World, and in the World to come. Seaſonably diſcourſed, and earneſtly preſſed upon this Licentious Age.</p>
            <p>ΠΛΑΝΗΛΟΓΙΑ: A Succinct and Seaſonable Diſcourſe of the Occaſions, Cauſes, Nature, Riſe, Growth, and Remedies of Mental Errors. Written ſome Months ſince; and now made publick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both for the healing and prevention of the Sins and Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcandal of Religion, hardening of the Wicked<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and obſtruction of Reformation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto are ſubjoined by way of Appendix: <hi>I. Vindiciarum Vindex:</hi> Being a Succinct, but full Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Philip Cary</hi>'s weak and impertinent Exceptions to my <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae Legis &amp; Foederis. II.</hi> A <hi>Synopſis</hi> of Ancient and Modern <hi>Antinomian Errors,</hi> with Scriptural Arguments and Reaſons againſt them. <hi>III.</hi> A <hi>Sermon</hi> compoſed for the preventing and healing of Rents and Diviſions in the Churches of Chriſt. <hi>Both by</hi> John Flavell, <hi>Preacher of the Goſpel at</hi> Dartmouth <hi>in</hi> Deven.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
